Guide to the György Kepes papers M1796
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Series 3: Books
  - 3.3. Light Book photographs [as labeled]
    - Sculptures (Box 69, Folder 2)
      17 photos: 13 pictures of Erwin Hauer Light diffusion Sculptures, Rythem Plastique eu Amourante, Horseshoe stone " The Yoke", 2 undescribed photos.
    - Sculptures (Box 73, Folder 3)
      30 Photographs: Mural project- complex light reflections, Barcelona table, Statue of Hermes, 9 photos by Masayuki Nagare, Ceiling of Josenji Temple, photo of mechanical statue, interior of Caracas University, Escuela de Petroeo del Zulia, Lampe II- le bio Ljubljana (1954), Max Bill Sculptures- Zurich, Lumina Stands- photo by John D. Schiff, Darwin Wedding Chapel III- Martha Jackson Gallery, Louis Nevelson- Original Wall for Corridor, Otto Pienne- Onion Flower, Doremi- by Garson Kanin, " The Firstborn"- Christopher Fry, "View from the Bridge"- Arthur Miller, "JB"- Archibald Mac Leish, 4 undescribed photos.
    - Surface Modeling (Box 68, Folders 1-2)
      7 photographs of exterior relief architectual details: Limestone Inscription, Middle Kingdom; wall relief, Palace of Ashiur-Nasir-Pal II; arachnoidis zelandiae; Sophie Tauber-Arp, Coqullies, 1938; 3 undescribed; 12 photographs of wall and door exterior reliefs details: 7 photographs of corrugated material, photo St. John's Baptistry "Humilitas", photo Masayuki Nagare outdoor mural, photo manufacturing plant- West Façade, photo of bulding with staircase, Chapel at Ronchamp.
    - Window Aperatures (Box 72, Folders 5-6)
      23 photographs: 6 photos of Hagia Sophia form Library of Congress, Torin Castello by S. Lorenzo, Gossau Plant, Interior of Church and Dome inside the U.N by Ezra Stellar Associates, Giovanni Piransei- interior of Pantheon(x2), Granada- Alhambra- Mirador de Darraxa(x2), 3 undescribed photos on cardboard, 2 photos of St. Remy de Baccarat, 5 undescribed photos of window aperature; 21 photographs: Hagi City Hall- Tokyo Japan, St. Sebastians Church, Hagia Sohpia East Corridor, Basilica di S. Apollinare- B. Anderson, Palazzo Ducale- Finestra della Sala,St. Remy de Baccarat- F. Stahly, Multi lens glass door (1929), St. Johns Abbey- Collegeville Minnosota, Assisi- Chiesa Abbaziale di S. Pietro, 3 photos from Toronto School of Architecture- by Annan of Glascow, 2 photos of Ciudad University in Caracas, 7 undescribed photos of interior window aperatures.
  - 3.4. Language of Vision
    This landmark text by Kepes was first published by Paul Theobald in 1944. Most of the material in the collection concerns negotiations for various reprints of the book.
    - Language of Vision Contract, 1945 (Box 51, Folder 2)
      Letter from Kepes' editor and contract. Photocopies.
    - Language of Vision Contracts, 1961 (Box 51, Folder 7)
      Copy of publication contract for Language of Vision between Kepes and Paul Theobald & Company.
    - Language of Vision Negatives (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Most are 3x4 and 4x5; some smaller. Most contained in individual wax paper or manila envelopes.
      Box of 64 negatives presumably for reproduction in "Language of Vision" and possibly later Kepes publications. Some include handwritten captions or citations. Most reproduce images from prior publications and include original text or caption copy. Masking was applied to some negatives in preparation for reproduction. Images include Vincent Van Gogh drawing, promotional image of Charlie Chaplin in City Lights, illustration of a Japanese garden, Picasso drawing, Poussin's "Rape of the Sabine Women," Chinese seals, images of animal structures, topography, and many others. Includes slides of Kepes's own drawings in "Language of Vision."
    - Language of Vision Gouaches (Box 50, Folder 1)
      Five undated gouaches illustrating The Language of Vision.
    - Language of Vision, permissions for Italian edition, circa 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Note: These permissions letters do not correspond to the original box label.
    - Paul Theobald correspondence (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Correspondence with Paul Theobald Company re: French edition and paperback editions.
    - Greek translation correspondence, 1981 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      Two letters between Kepes and Professor Dimitris Mytaras from a Greek school about matters relating to publishing.
    - Jean Koefoed Correspondence, 1991 (Box 51, Folder 5)
      Correspondence from Jean Koefoed of International Publishing Corporation about the possiblity of re-publishing Language of Vision.
    - Copyright Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 51, Folder 6)
      Correspondence among Kepes and various lawyers about copyright and publication rights for Language of Vision.
    - Reprint correspondence, 1992-1993 (Box 51, Folder 9)
      Correspondence and Publication Agreement for a reprint of Language of Vision.
    - Language of Vision correspondence, 1945 (Box 51, Folder 13)
      Correspondence - mostly handwritten.
    - Language of Vision Correspondence, 1960-1973 (Box 51, Folder 14)
    - Language of Vision Hungarian Translation (Box 43, Folder 17)
      Typescript in Hungarian.
  - 3.5. New Landscape in Art and Science
    The New Landscape was first published by Paul Theobald in 1956.
    - New Landscape notes (Box 16, Folder 8)
      Hand-written notes on The New Landscape.
    - Theobald, Fassett, New Landscape correspondence, 1953-1973 (Box 51, Folder 10)
      Correspondence relating to publication of The New Landscape. Bulk is from 1953-54.
    - New Landscape correspondence, 1953-1957 (Box 51, Folder 11)
      Bulk 1954. Folder was originally called "Contract The New Landscape," but contains no contract.
    - New Landscape, permissions for first edition (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Note: These permissions letters do not correspond to the original box label. Circa early 1950s.
    - New Landscape, permissions for Hungarian edition, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Note: These permissions letters do not correspond to the original box label. Letters dated c. 1973 and 1974 from Josef Albers, Harold Edgerton, and from various museums. Document confirming verbal permission from Herb Comess. Some include related invoices.
    - Hans M. Wingler German edition correspondence (Box 14, Folder 4)
      Two copies of letter explaining shipment of photographic material for the planned German edition of The New Landscape. Lists 456 black and white illustrations used in Hungarian volume and 7 additional illustrations not used in Hungarian volume, all shipped to the Bauhaus-Archive.
    - New Landscape, photographs for German edition (Box 14, Folders 1-3, Box 13, Folders 1-5)
      Mostly 8x10 b/w glossy silver gelatin prints.
      40 photographs, some on panels, of works presumably reproduced in the German edition of The New Landscape. Note: some photographs may also have been reproduced in the Vision + Value series, as identified on stamps on reverse.
    - The New Landscape [Keppler manuscript] (Box 28, Folder 27)
      Manuscript of a text by Herbert Keppler. May not be related to book.
    - New Landscape image lists (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Note: These lists do not correspond to the original box label. 3 checklists for image captions in "The New Landscape." One list includes alterations to the order of images pasted with rubber cement over the original list.
    - New Landscape 11x14 (Box 59, Folder 2)
    - New Landscape photographs Ph4 (Box 59, Folders 4-5, Box 60, Folder 1)
      Also labeled Ph4. Photographic prints.
      General
      60/1 is "Physically located in same box as Series II, Box 19.2 because of large size" according to original processor. Box 19 is "Daily Reminders, 1988-9."
    - Photographs (Box 63, Folders 3-4)
      Originally in a box with the title "New Landscape Discarded Photos," which has been crossed out. Photographic prints.
    - New Landscape, extra copies of illustrations [not related to book?] (Box 8, Folders 10-12)
      Note: 53 photographs in original order. Although original box was labeled "The New Landscape," most images are dated from 1960s and are not related to the original edition of The New Landscape. Photographs of works by Constantin Brancusi, Max Bill, Jack Burnham, Guenter Uecker, Mies van der Rohe, Georges Vantongerloo, David Smith, Heinz Mack, Marcel Breuer, and Julio Le Parc. Photographs by Nishan Bichajian. Includes student work produced at MIT in the Light and Color course. Also includes miscellaneous scientific imagery.
    - The New Landscape photographs (Box 3, Folder 13)
      31 photographs for images reproduced in The New Landscape; mostly scientific imagery but includes a few art historical images. Lissuous figures, micrographs, images of crystals and minerals and x-ray diffraction photographs. Some photographs include stamped or handwritten notations suggesting they are from the Vision + Value series not The New Landscape.
      Mostly 8 x 10 black and white glossy photographs; some smaller formats. 1 matte board with pasted photographs.
    - New Landscape negatives (Box 3, Folder 12)
      14 large format negatives for images reproduced in The New Landscape; mostly scientific imagery but includes 1 possible Kepes photogram.
      Large format negatives.
    - New Landscape Negatives (Box 65, Folder 5)
    - New Landscape Negatives N16 (Box 67, Folder 3)
      Originally in a metal box with this label. Also labeled N16.
    - New Landscape negatives N17 (Box 67, Folder 6)
      Originally in a metal box with this label. Also labeled N17. Some negatives still in box.
  - 3.6. Vision & Value series
    In 1965-1966, Kepes edited a set of six anthologies, published as the Vision + Value Series by George Braziller. Each volume contained essays by artists, designers, architects and scientists, as well as many photographs and illustrations. The volumes were as follows: The Education of Vision; Structure in Art and Science; The Nature and Art of Motion; Module, Symmetry, Proportion, Rhythm; Sign, Image, Symbol; and The Man-Made Object.
    - Vision and Value series correspondence with George Braziler re: Italian edition (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Vision and Value photographs, Environment (Box 6, Folders 12-14)
      Note: 63 photographs in original order. Photographs of works by Maxime Descombin, Wen-Ying Tsai, Max Bill, Simon Nicholson, Geny Dignac, Masayuki Nagare, Dan Flavin, and others. Roger J. Chen scientific photograpy of ice crystal formation. Photographs of power plants, refineries, and heavy industry from the Tennessee Valley Authority and Standard Oil Company. Photographs by William Garnet, Gyorgy Kepes, Martin S. Dworkin, Donald Olson, and others. Reproductions of photocollages by Friedrich St. Florian.
      Mostly 8X10 b/w glossy silver gelatin prints; includes some smaller sizes.
    - Vision and Value photographs, Arts of Participation (Box 6, Folders 15-17)
      Note: 115 photographs in original order. photographs of works by David Temiers, Stan Vanderbeek, and Jan Ossenbeck. Photographic documentation of events by Theo Botschuijver and Jeffrey Shaw, from the New York City Department of Cultural Affairs, and various images of dances, rituals, ceremonies, student protests, and parades. Includes images of the Wailing Wall, the Woodstock festival, Les Halles market in Paris, and many others. Also contains photographs by G. Duby, Dan Brody for the Harvard Crimson, Peter Moore, and others. Includes letter from Theo Botschuijver and Jeffrey Shaw re: photographs. Includes three pages of notes from G. Kepes re: captions for various Vision and Value publications. Postcard from the British Museum.
    - Vision and Value photographs, Arts of Participation (Box 7, Folders 1-3)
      Note: 114 photographs in original order. Continues previous set of folders but originally organized in separate Kodak box. Photographs by Robert Capa and many miscellaneous images. Photographs of works by Piotr Kowalski, Geny Dignac, and photographs form UPI, NASA, Standard Oil Company. Includes miscellaneous corresondence relating to photographs, checklist, and notes about captions and descriptions.
  - 3.7. Kepes books, published [mostly foreign press]
    - A látás nyelve (Gondolat 1979) (Box 98, Item 1)
    - La Estructura en el Arte y en la Cienca (Novaro 1970) (Box 98, Item 2)
    - A világ új képe a művészetben és a tudományban (Corvina 1979) (Box 98, Item 3)
    - Graphic forms; the arts as related to the book (Harvard University Press 1949) (Box 98, Item 4)
    - El Lenguaje de la Vision (Ediciones Infinito 1969) (Box 98, Item 5)
    - The New Landscape in Art and Science (Photographic Society of Japan) (Box 98, Item 6)
    - A közösségi művészet felé (Magvető Könyvkiadó 1978) (Box 98, Item 7)
- Series 4. Artwork
  - 4.1. Sketchbooks
    - Sketchbooks 1976, 1977, 1985, undated (Box 20)
      Six unfoldered sketchbooks containing some loose material, photographic negative, and a photographic print.
    - Sketchbooks 1966-1967, 1975, 1979, undated (Box 21)
      Four unfoldered sketchbooks.
    - Sketchbooks 1980, undated (Box 22)
      Four unfoldered sketchbooks. Includes a photographic negative, a painting stencil, and other loose material.
    - Sketchbooks 1976-7, 1979 (Box 23)
      Three unfoldered sketchbooks. Includes pasted-in printed, drawn and photographic material and pressed tree leaves.
    - Sketchbook, circa 1994 (Box 24)
      Date derived from newspaper clipping inserted into back cover. Contains sketches directly on pages as well as pasted-in material.
  - 4.2. Drawings and artwork
    - Drawings (Box 29, Folder 14)
      Various unlabeled and undated drawings. Some photocopies, some originals.
    - Printmaking plates [unfoldered] (Box 54, Folder 1)
      Four metal plates for an unknown work in an unknown printmaking medium.
    - Drawings, 1998 and undated (Box 55, Folder 1)
      Drawings by Rockne Krebs and presumably by Kepes.
    - Drawings and clippings (Box 55, Folder 3)
      Assorted drawings and clippings of works, all by Kepes.
    - Sketches (Tube 57)
      Four sketches in ink on modern parchment paper. They seem to be mock-ups of larger works. 4 total items.
    - Paintings (Box 118, Folders 1-5)
    - Paintings, architectural (2012-063) (Map-folder 188)
    - Paintings [approximately 11 unfoldered panels, mostly gouache] (Box 191)
    - Stained glass designs in watercolor (Box 190, Folder 3)
- Series 5. Exhibitions & events
  - 5.1. Event posters
    - posters, large (Map-folder 187)
    - posters, medium (Box 190, Folder 1)
    - posters, medium (Box 191, Folder 1)
  - 5.2. Kepes exhibitions, misc.
    - MIT exhibition photographs (Box 9, Folder 8)
      8x10 b/w glossy gelatin silver prints.
      5 photographs from "Light as a Creative Medium" exhibition, and from what appears to be a Kepes retrospective.
    - Kepes catalog photographs (Box 9, Folder 9)
      11 photographs reproducing pages from exhibition catalog of Boston Harbor Centennial environmental art projects.
    - Carpenter Light Exhibition negatives (Box 12, Folder 1)
      Negatives presumably used in the exhibition "Light as a Creative Medium" (Carpenter Center for the Visual Arts, Harvard) or its catalog. 96 negatives in envelopes; some labeled, some with printing instructions. 30 loose negatives; 1 glass negative. Includes some photographs with specific negatives and 3 loose photos.
    - Correspondence and Files, 1983-1988 (Box 25, Folder 2)
      Correspondence and files mostly related to business, including Kepes loaning photographs to exhibitions, as well as an installation piece for the Harvard Square T Station.
    - Exhibition Brochure, 1967 (Box 26, Folder 11)
      Publicity material for an exhibition of Kepes' paintings at the Lamont Gallery at The Phillips Exeter Academy in Exeter, NH on May 2-28, 1967.
    - Miscellaneous Publications 1981 and undated (Box 27, Folder 15)
      Material concerning exhibitions, auctions, and Kepes' biography.
    - Wichita Exhibition Lecture, 1979 (Box 27, Folder 20)
      Shipping invoice for 34 paintings sent to Wichita Art Museum for exhibition of Kepes' work. Includes list of the paintings.
    - Exhibition Materials, 1974-1977 (Box 27, Folder 21)
      Includes a review of a Kepes show in Trieste in 1976, possible commitments for Kepes in August 1974, and materials relating to a 1977 exhibition at Dartmouth College.
    - Exhibition Materials and miscellaneous, 1960s-1980s (Box 28, Folder 3)
      Publicity materials for exhibitions of Kepes and others, as well as a clipping of a Kepes publication in the Architectural Record for May, 1965, an article about a Center for Advanced Study in the Visual Arts project, and a photograph of what appears to be brain scan images.
    - Robinson Gallery, 1977 (Box 30, Folder 2)
      Correspondence, consignment forms, and other material relating to business with Robinson Galleries.
    - Exhibition Materials, 1973-1981 (Box 30, Folder 3)
      Publicity materials and clippings related to various exhibitions of Kepes' work.
    - Exhibition Publicity 1974-1985, undated (Box 30, Folder 6)
      Various unrelated exhibition materials. One sheet was originally in a folder called "G.K. Biography."
    - Publications 1982, undated (Box 30, Folder 12)
      Postcard, publicity material for Institutute for Independent Study at Radcliffe, and publicity material for a group exhibition of which Kepes was a part.
    - ICP Exhibition, 1977 (Box 30, Folder 24)
      Two letters about an exhibition.
    - Printed material and clippings, 1960s-1970s (Box 30, Folder 28)
      Includes a large number of press releases, many having to do with exhibitions.
    - Printed Material 1973-1978, undated (Box 33, Folder 23)
      Mostly exhibition publicity material. Also a printed article by Kepes.
    - Galleries, 1994-1998 (Box 38, Folders 5-6)
      Correspondence and publicity material. Involves both Georgy and Juliet Kepes.
    - Light Exhibition Quotes (Box 38, Folder 8)
      Typed and carbon copy quotes of others' writings.
    - Correspondence, Saidenberg Gallery, 1977-1986 (Box 38, Folders 24-25)
    - Triennale - Blueprints, Photos, Information, 1968 (Box 39, Folder 3)
      Correspondence and drawings related to the 1968 Milan Triennale.
    - Correspondence, Paris Museum of Modern Art Review and Exhibition, 1980-1982 (Box 39, Folder 4)
    - Fliers, cards, etc. Early: School of Design, Kuh, etc., 1939-1950 (Box 50, Folder 4)
      Some materials are undated, but bulk are from 1940s. Publicity materials for exhibitions.
    - Gallery Correspondence, 1964-1975 (Box 52, Folder 1)
      Correspondence with people at various galleries about sales of paintings, etc.
    - Gallery Correspondence, 1958-1982 (Box 52, Folder 2)
    - Gallery Moos, 1968-1976 (Box 52, Folders 3-4)
      Correspondence between Kepes, lawyers, and representatives of Gallery Moos.
    - Publicity Materials, 1969 (Box 52, Folder 5)
      Publications relating to exhibitions from Alpha Gallery, empty envelopes from Gallery Moos.
    - Bertrand Russell Peace Foundation Exhibition, 1972-12 (Box 58, Folder 16)
      Photocopies.
    - Kepes Collection at Hurst Gallery postcard (Box 105, Folder 22)
    - Saidenberg Gallery painting list, 1983 (Box 105, Folder 24)
  - 5.3. Kepes group show exhibitions [chronological]
    - undated (Box 95, Folder 5)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 95, Folder 6)
    - 1960-1966 (Box 95, Folder 7)
    - 1967-1970 (Box 95, Folder 8)
    - 1971-1975 (Box 96, Folder 1)
    - 1976-1978 (Box 96, Folder 2)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 96, Folder 3)
    - 1987-1999 (Box 96, Folder 4)
  - 5.4. Kepes one man show exhibitions [chronological]
    - undated (Box 94, Folder 1)
    - 1939-1955 (Box 94, Folder 2)
    - 1958-1959 (Box 94, Folder 3)
    - 1960-1962 (Box 94, Folder 4)
    - 1963-1966 (Box 94, Folder 5)
    - 1967-1968 (Box 94, Folder 6)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 94, Folder 7)
    - 1973 (Box 94, Folder 8)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 94, Folder 9)
    - 1976 (Box 94, Folder 10)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 94, Folder 11)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 95, Folder 1)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 95, Folder 2)
    - 1985-1989 (Box 95, Folder 3)
    - 1991-2008 (Box 95, Folder 4)
- Series 6. Notes and research files
  - 6.1. Notes and research: general
    Contains a variety of material written or assembled by Kepes for research purposes, including handwritten notes, manuscripts typescripts, published items, and notes not by Kepes. See related "Assorted Material" series of unsorted folders (less of Kepes' writing).
    - Manuscripts, 1968 (Tube 57)
      Very oversize diagram rolled around tube - found with other oversize items from folder 2 that are located in map case. The diagram is of a "Plan of Ceiling Lights" for a "City at Night" Thomas McNulty, Architects. 1 item. "Manuscripts" was the original title of the box. Continuation of above. Large-format but smaller. Other diagrams about the "City at Night" lights. 8 total items.
    - Notes on light technology and light windows (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous notes on light technology (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Handwritten notes. References Photoelastic Walk, types of luminescence, and turbulence.
    - Miscellaneous typed pages (Box 5, Folder 4)
      2 typed pages from larger manuscripts.
    - Modulation, master copy, 1965-02-26 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Includes one miscellaneous page that may not be part of this manuscript.
    - Miscellaneous notes, intrinsic symbols (Box 6, Folder 11)
      One page of notes in blue pen with pencil drawings on back.
    - Light Modulation manuscripts (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Typed manuscripts, many with handwritten notations and edits.
    - Light Modulation typescripts, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      Multiple copies of manuscripts titled "Light and Color - Modulation" or "Light Modulation" or similar, with many revision and versions.
    - Vision fundamentals notes (Box 9, Folder 7)
      Handwritten notes on "Environmental art," "Participation" dated 2/18/69, "sound," "homeostasis," "scale," "light," and many other topics. Typed notes on light, typed outline, one page of typed notes dated 11/13/68, b/w glossy silver gelatin photograph of a nuclear reactor control room, typed sheet titled "Summary of the Activities of the Center for Interdisciplinary (I-D) Creativity" dated July 1, 1971-June 30, 1972, miscellaneous typed quotations, and much more. Notes appear out of order.
    - Light Modulation Notes and Typescripts (Box 16, Folder 3)
      Hand-written notes and typed material - one document is in Italian.
    - New Orleans notes (Box 16, Folder 5)
      Photocopy of a series of hand-written notes.
    - Notes and Typescripts on Environment (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Artificial Light 1947, undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
      Typescripts, notes, and publications dealing with artificial light.
    - Notes on Light (Box 16, Folder 10)
      Hand-written notes and lists on various light-related subjects.
    - Light and Color Notes and Typewriters 1965, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
      Many of the typescripts have hand-written notes on them. Includes information about Times Square.
    - Copies 1964-5, 1972 (Box 16, Folder 13)
      Copies of various lectures and other works by Kepes - items in English as well as German and Hungarian - some hand-written notes.
    - Light, Pollution, Communism - Miscellaneous Typescripts 1965-8, undated (Box 16, Folder 14)
      Copies, with handwritten notes, of various texts on pollution, light, and communism. Authors include Thomas Young, Dziga Viertov, and Mao Zedong.
    - Corrected Manuscript on the Modern World (Box 16, Folder 16)
      Extensively corrected manuscript about achieving equilibrium in the modern world. Corrections are in Italian.
    - Notes - Perception, Emotion (Box 16, Folder 17)
      Three pages of hand-written notes on various subjects surrounding perception and emotion.
    - Notes on Art and Scale (Box 17, Folder 1)